Guide to the Jessie Vanderbilt Simons Papers, 1870-1936 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Jessie Vanderbilt Simons papers 1870-1936 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Simons, Jessie Vanderbilt
6.5 Linear Feet 1000 Items
Jessie Vanderbilt McNamee was born in 1874 to a wealthy family residing in Staten Island, New York (Richmond County). In 1901 she married Charles Dewar Simons(1874-1922) and they had one child, Charles Dewar, Jr. Ms. Simons served as a volunteer ambulance driver with the Dongan Hills Motor Corps; helped found and served as the ranking member of the Richmond County chapter of the Red Cross Motor Corps during World War I; served as Vice President of the National Federated Workers for Disabled Soldiers; and was an active member of the Veteran Association of Women War Workers. Her travels throughout Europe during the 1920s and 1930s are documented in diaries, correspondence, and other materials in this collection. Ms. Simons was a friend and neighbor of Alice Austen, a noted photographer who also served in the Richmond County Motor Corps.
The Jessie Vanderbilt Simons papers contain materials dating from 1870 to 1936, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1890 to 1936. Materials in the collection primarily document Simons' travels through Europe during the 1920s and 1930s and her work with the Richmond County chapter of the American Red Cross Motor Corps. Twenty-nine yearly diaries detail daily life, family life, travel, participation in the Motor Corps, and other philanthropic activities. Correspondence with her son, family, and friends is also included; as are receipts, invoices, and other financial materials, primarily from travel to Europe; correspondence, printed materials, a scrapbook, and other items documenting Simons' service with the American Red Cross Motor Corps; material relating to friend, photographer, and fellow Motor Corps member Alice Austen; and photographs.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Jessie Vanderbilt Simons Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2007.
Biographical Note
Jessie Vanderbilt McNamee was born in 1874 to a wealthy family residing in Staten Island, New York (Richmond County). In 1901 she married Charles Dewar Simons(1874-1922) and they had one child, Charles Dewar, Jr. Ms. Simons served as a volunteer ambulance driver with the Dongan Hills Motor Corps; helped found and served as the ranking member of the Richmond County chapter of the Red Cross Motor Corps during World War I; served as Vice President of the National Federated Workers for Disabled Soldiers; and was an active member of the Veteran Association of Women War Workers. Her travels throughout Europe during the 1920s and 1930s are documented in diaries, correspondence, and other materials in this collection. Ms. Simons was a friend and neighbor of Alice Austen, a noted photographer who also served in the Richmond County Motor Corps.
Collection Overview
The Jessie Vanderbilt Simons papers contain materials dating from 1870 to 1936, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1890 to 1936. Materials in the collection primarily document Simons' travels through Europe during the 1920s and 1930s and her work with the Richmond County chapter of the American Red Cross Motor Corps. Twenty-nine yearly diaries detail daily life, family life, travel, participation in the Motor Corps, and other philanthropic activities. Correspondence with her son, family, and friends is also included; as are receipts, invoices, and other financial materials, primarily from travel to Europe; correspondence, printed materials, a scrapbook, and other items documenting Simons' service with the American Red Cross Motor Corps; material relating to friend, photographer, and fellow Motor Corps member Alice Austen; and photographs.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
American Red Cross -- Women's Motor Corps
Austen, Alice -- 1866-1952
Diaries
Europe -- Description and travel
Invoices
Photographs
Photographers -- United States
Receipts (financial records)
Richmond County (NY.) -- History
Scrapbook
Simons family
Simons, Jessie Vanderbilt
Staten Island (New York, NY.) -- History
Voluntarism -- United States
Women -- New York (State) -- History -- 20th century
Women -- United States -- History -- 20th century
Women artists
Women volunteers in social service -- United States
World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- United States
World War, 1914-1918 -- Women
Contents of Collection
- Jessie Vanderbilt Simons papers, 1870-1936 and undated, 11 Boxes
  The Jessie Vanderbilt Simons papers contain materials dating from 1870 to 1936, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1890 to 1936. Materials in the collection primarily document Simons' travels through Europe during the 1920s and 1930s and her work with the Richmond County chapter of the American Red Cross Motor Corps. Twenty-nine yearly diaries detail daily life, family life, travel, participation in the Motor Corps, and other philanthropic activities. Correspondence with her son, family, and friends is also included; as are receipts, invoices, and other financial materials, primarily from travel to Europe; correspondence, printed materials, a scrapbook, and other items documenting Simons' service with the American Red Cross Motor Corps; material relating to friend, photographer, and fellow Motor Corps member Alice Austen; and photographs. Files are arranged alphabetically.
  - American Red Cross, 1914-1922 and undated, (5 folders) (Box 1)
    Jessie Vanderbilt Simons initially served as Captain of the Dongan Hills Motor Corps, which was later incorporated into the Richmond County Motor Corps. Included are signed letters dated 1914 from Secretary of State Robert Lansing and Secretary of the Navy Josephus Daniels responding to letters from Simons concerning transportation of Americans attempting to return from England due to wartime conditions. Other correspondence relates to her service in the Motor Corps and her dismissal as Captain of the organization.
  - Alice Austen, 1880s, 1896, 1931-1934, 1978-1987, and undated, (2 folders)
  - Correspondence, 1890-1936 and undated, (Folders 1-2 of 4)
  - Correspondence, 1890-1936 and undated, (Folders 3-4 of 4) (Box 2)
  - Diaries, 1870-1873, 1890-1893, (5 items)
  - Diaries, 1895-1902, (6 items) (Box 3)
  - Diaries, 1903-1916, (8 items) (Box 4)
  - Diaries, 1918-1925, (9 items) (Box 5)
  - Diaries, 1926-1934, (9 items) (Box 6)
  - Diary, 1935 (Box 7)
  - Financial and related materials, 1913-1936 and undated, (6 folders)
    A large number of receipts and invoices among these materials are in German.
  - Photographs, 1890s-1930s (Box 8)
    Photographs are of Jessie Vanderbilt Simons (4), the Simons home (1), Charles Dewar Simons, Jr. (6), Jessie Vanderbilt Simons and Charles Dewar Simons, Jr. (2), American Red Cross activities (4), Charles Simons' parents (1), Jessie Vanderbilt Simons and Charles Simons (1), Charles Simons (1). Five unidentified photographs are also included.
  - Photographs, 1890s-1930s (Box 9)
    Photographs are of Jessie Vanderbilt Simons (2), Jessie Vanderbilt Simons and Charles Dewar Simons, Jr. (1), American Red Cross activities (2), Charles Simons' father (1), Charles Simons' parents (2), Jessie Vanderbilt Simons and her sister, Faith (1), Faith (5), Charles Simons (3).
  - Photographs, 1890s-1930s (Box 10)
    Photographs are of Jessie Vanderbilt Simons' sister, Faith (2).
  - Scrapbook, 1917-1920 (Box 11)
    Documents Simons' service with the American Red Cross, the American Red Cross Motor Corps, the Richmond County Motor Corps, and the National Federated Workers for Disabled Soldiers.